George Washington Truett papers, Inclusive: 1891-1942, undated, Bulk: 1891-1942, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
George Washington Truett papers
Inclusive: 1891-1942, undated, Bulk: 1891-1942, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
95
Truett, George Washington, 1867 - 1944
9 folders
The George Washington Truett papers contains personal correspondence, literary productions, photographs, films, and audio recordings pertaining to G. W. Truett, a Baptist minister in the early twentieth century.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
George Washington Truett an acclaimed Baptist minister, was born in Clay County, North Carolina, on 1867 May 6. His parents were Charles L. and Mary R. (Kimsey) Truett. From an early age, Truett showed an interest in academics. He attended the Hayesville Academy near his home from 1875 to 1885. The direction of his life fundamentally changed after his conversion experience at a local evangelical revival in 1886.
From that point forward, Truett devoted his life to the sharing of the gospel. In 1889, he followed his parents to Whitewright, Texas. While attending Grayson Junior College, Truett taught Sunday school and often filled in for the pastor at the local Baptist church. He was officially ordained as a Baptist minister in 1890.
His powerful oratorical skills added to Truett’s growing reputation in Texas. In 1890, Truett joined the staff at Baylor University and was influential in paying a university debt of $92,000 in two years. He enrolled at the university as a student in 1893. To pay for his education, Truett preached at nearby East Waco Baptist Church. He married Josephine Jenkins on 1894 June 28. The couple had three daughters.
After graduating in 1897, Truett accepted the pastorate at the First Baptist Church in Dallas. He held this position for forty-seven years, increasing the church membership from 715 to 7,804. During World War 1, Truett was appointed by President Woodrow Wilson to preach to American troops in Europe. On 1920 May 16, Truett delivered one of his most famous sermons on the steps of the U.S. Capitol concerning the principles of religious freedom and the separation of church and state. He was president of the Southern Baptist Convention from 1927-1929 as well as the president of Baptist World Alliance from 1934-1939. Truett was also able to publish many of his sermons in book form. Truett died in Dallas on 1944 July 7.
The George W. Truett Theological Seminary, found on the Baylor University campus, was chartered in 1991 and named for Reverend Truett. The inaugural class graduated six years later.
Scope and Content
The George Washington Truett papers ranges from 1891 to 1942. The materials highlight Truett’s involvement with Baylor University as well as the work of Baptists in Texas. Audio recordings of a few of his sermons can be found using the index in Box 1, Folder 10.
Arrangement
This small collection has been organized into four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Photographic Materials, and IV. Audio Recordings. The correspondence is organized chronologically. The literary productions are organized according to the type of material. The photographic materials and audio recordings are organized topically.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 95. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Pat M. Neff collection, Inclusive: 1847-1952, Bulk: 1920-1947
Related references
“Affiliations, Accreditations, and History.” Baylor University. Accessed 2012 February 28.
Baker, Eugene W. To Light the Ways of Time: An Illustrated History of Baylor University. Waco: Baylor University Press, 1987.
Perez, Joan Jenkins. “George W. Truett.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 February 28.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Truett, George W. (George Washington). 1867-1944.
Subjects
Baptists -- Sermons.; Baptists -- Texas -- History.; Baptists -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Photographs.; Programs.
- Correspondence, 1891-1942; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This folder contains correspondence written by and to George W. Truett. Letters from the president of Grayson College and from Richard Holmes are included. This series is in good condition.
  - General, 1891-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Literary Productions, 1920, undated; 2
  This series consists of a Baylor University commencement program, five religious tracts, and a memorial to George W. Truett. These materials are in good condition.
  - Program: Baylor University: Commencement, 1920 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tracts: Religious, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorial: George Washington Truett, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photographic Materials, 1916-1938, undated; 3
  This series contains photographic materials pertaining to George W. Truett, Baptists, Baylor University, and the Franklin family. These materials are in good condition.
  - Photographs: George Washington Truett, 1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs: Baptists, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographss: George Washington Truett and Frances Franklin, 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs: Photos: Baylor University: Jesse Franklin, 1916-1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs: Jesse Franklin, 1919-1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)